Whoops, whoops, whoops, whoops, whoops, whoops, wait one second. All right, let's
assume we're on.
בוקר טוב Boker tov live from New York.
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah in the fascinating rabbinic cookbook, we are at
the bottom of דף ל"ז עמוד ב'. Daf Lamed Zayin Amud Bet.
I want to share something that's not at all related to our
topic. Last night there was a fabulous performance by Dan Raichel in
Manhattan and at the end of the performance everybody says הדרן הדרן.
Hadran, Hadran. You know what that's what people say in Israel when
you want encore, הדרן, Hadran, straight from גמרא מפורשת Gemara Meforeshet as
we say. Okay, we are nine lines from the bottom, three lines
from the wide lines, והשלקות, vehashlakot,
and Dan ended yesterday by explaining the שלקות shlakot that they appear
in מסכת ברכות Masechet Berachot was a ברכה bracha of the אדמה,
Adamah, ברכה bracha of the שלקות shlakot is אדמה. Adamah. It's like
a vegetable soup that's made from the vegetables and then the vegetables
were taken out, so like a broth.
So this is our question right now, this is our food here.
It's a food that is mixed water and food, what do we
do with it? And from there we're going to discuss some aspects
of בישולי עכו"ם Bishulei Akum of cooking by non-Jews.
We'll immediately before even going into the גמרא Gemara
skip sideways to the תוספות Tosfot who's asking where's the גמרא Gemara
מנהני מילי min hanilei like where how do we know this? Because
there is no פסוק מפורש, pasuk meforesh, there is a sort of
פסוק pasuk and we'll look at it in just a minute. And
if you look in the
תוספות Tosfot seven lines into the תוספות Tosfot
and you can see that he says גזרו עליה מטעם חתנות ועל
הפת לא גזרו משום שלא שייך בה חתנות.
gazru aleiha mitam khatnut veal
hapat lo gazru mishum shelo shayach bei khatnut.
So the main concern with this cooking joint cooking
is relationship. There is also aspects of what do different people put
in the food like if I give my cooking to somebody I
don't trust there can be
poisons, dangers, non-kosher like variety of things that we can imagine by
living with somebody that we have a mistrust with. But תוספות Tosfot
at least outspoken reasoning is חתנות. khatnut. Okay, where do we have
this idea of the שלקות? shlakot? אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן אמר קרא. Amar Rabbi Chiya Bar Abba, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
Amar Kra. We have a פסוק pasuk and our פסוק pasuk is
here in the beginning of ספר דברים Sefer Devarim when Moshe is
retelling the story of going to סיחון מלך האמורי, Sichon Melech Haemori,
the King of the Amorite. We're in דברים Devarim chapter 2, 27,
he says אעברה בארצך בדרך בדרך אלך לא אסור ימין ושמאל אוכל
בכסף תשבירני ואכלתי ומים בכסף תתני ושתיתי רק אעברה ברגלי. evra bearzecha
baderech, baderech elech, lo asur yamin usmol, ochel bakesef tashbireni veachalti, umayim
bakesef titeni veshatiti, rak evra beraglai. Okay,
so we have from Moshe, we're in the beginning 27, we're at
the bottom of ברגלי. beraglai.
רגלא. ragla. ברגלי. beragli. רגלי. ragli. Thank you.
We're in the bottom of דף ל"ז עמוד ב' Daf Lamed Zayin
Amud Bet and we're looking at a פסוק pasuk that is a
prooftext sort of for the שלקות. shlakot. And so now we're going
to look at this word כמים, kamayim, what does it mean? מה
מים שלא נשתנו אף אוכל שלא נשתנו. Ma mayim shelo nishtanu, af
ochel shelo nishtanu. So what kind of food can I eat from
the עובדי כוכבים? ovdei kochavim? Just like water doesn't change, then I
am allowed to eat foods that don't change. So now let's look
at some foods that don't change and see what we do with
them. אלא מעתה חטים ועשאן קליות הכי נמי דאסורין? Ella meata chitin
veasaan kliyot, hachi nami deasurin? So what do we do with wheat
kernels that have been roasted? Does that mean that they're now forbidden
because they
which category will they fall into, the changed or the not changed?
וכי תימא הכי נמי והתניא חטים ועשאן קליות מותרין. Vechitema hachi nami,
vehatanya chitin veasaan kliyot mutarin.
We have a ברייתא braita that tells us that חטים, chitin, the
grains, that we
roast. I wouldn't say that parching grains really changes it. That's exactly
the discussion. So
if where is the line of the change and I think that's
always—grains to flour
making into bread is some change.
Let's put some mileage into the text and then see where it's
going. Okay. So this is exactly what we're contrasting. Are the grains
changing by being parched or roasted or are they not? אלא כמים,
Ella kamayim, like water. So what exactly is it like water? מה
מים שלא נשתנו מברייתן אף אוכל שלא נשתנה מברייתו. Ma mayim shelo
nishtanu mibriyatan af ochel shelo nishtana mibriyato.
So let's just hold that thought because that's exactly what the גמרא
Gemara is going to try to unpack where is the line between
something that changes and something that doesn't change. Okay,
we have a חומש Chumash here, we need a פסוק. Pasuk. Okay.
אלא מעתה חיטין וטחנן הכי נמי אסורין. Ella me'ata chitin utchanan hachi
nami asurin.
So what about grains that are grounded? They're not cooked but they
are going through a process of טחינה. techina. Will they also be
אסורין? asurin? וכי תימא הכי נמי והתניא חיטין ועשאן קליות הקמחים והסלתות
שלהם מותרין. Vechi teima hachi nami vehatanya chitin ve'asaan kliyot hakmachim vehasaltot
shelahem mutarin.
We are taught that something that is grounded is permitted.
בוקר טוב. Boker tov. אלא כמים. Ella kamayim. So back to the
אלא כמים. Ella kamayim. What exactly do we mean by like water?
What process the water is going to that doesn't change them that
is relevant to our cooking? מה מים שלא נשתנו מברייתן על ידי
האור אף אוכל שלא נשתנה מברייתו על ידי האור.
Ma mayim shelo nishtanu mibriyatan al yedei ha'or af
ochel shelo nishtana mibriyato al yedei ha'or. So we're looking for food
that doesn't change by cooking, not that doesn't change by grinding but
that doesn't change by cooking. מדי אור כתיב? Midei or ketiv? Does
it say that in the verse? The verse doesn't say that. The
verse it says about משה Moshe going through סיחון מלך האמורי Sichon
Melech ha'Emori and he says I want food and talks about food
and water. אלא מדרבנן וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא. Ella miderabbanan vekra asmachta be'alma.
So the really this whole איסור issur is from דרבנן derabbanan from
the derivations or reality of life. So and you can see in
רש״י Rashi on the side that
in the top...
in
the top of ל״ח עמוד א׳, lamed-chet amud aleph, רש״י Rashi says,
אלא מדרבנן וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא פרש רש״י דרבנן גזור משום דחייש שמא
יאכילנו דברים טמאים ויותר היה נראה לפרש הטעם משום חתנות. Ella miderabbanan
vekra asmachta be'alma peireish Rashi derabbanan gazru mishum dechayish shema ya'achilennu devarim
tme'im veyoter haya nireh lefareish hatam mishum chatnut.
Oh,
sorry, sorry, you're right. אוי אוי אוי. Oy oy oy.
Thank you. תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot is interesting. I will deal with
it in just a minute. Let's go back to רש״י. Rashi. Sorry,
on the right side. שלא יהא ישראל רגיל אצלו במאכל ובמשתה ויאכילנו
דבר טמא. Shelo yehei Yisrael ragil etzlo bema'achal uvimishteh veya'achilennu davar tamei.
So there's two things. One is the רגילות regilut like being used
to eating at somebody else and then from there
something טמא tamei is going to be eaten. I want to bring
from
the—which is interesting you would have thought that you know חתנות בנותיהם
chatnut bnoteihem that's what—so
תוספות Tosafot talks about חתנות chatnut and רש״י Rashi talks about רגיל
אצלו ragil etzlo and ויאכילנו דבר טמא. veya'achilennu davar tamei.
Look, I believe a lot of the commentaries on the background of
the era they lived, not very different but whatever possibly things that
they experienced not just text. So תוספות Tosafot goes with the חתנות,
chatnut, רש״י Rashi goes with the רגיל, ragil, maybe from the רגיל
ragil will be חתנות chatnut etc. etc. Okay.
Notice in the תוספות Tosafot and sorry for my earlier mess up.
Look at the תוספות Tosafot third line okay,
second and a half. היה נראה לפרש הטעם משום חתנות וכן פירש
הקונטרס.
Haya nireh lefareish hatam mishum chatnut
vechen peireish hakuntres. So this is רש״י. Rashi. So right, this is
רש״י Rashi talks about to be רגיל ragil and to eat. But
then he brings a quote from Rabbi אברהם בן רבי דוד Avraham
ben Rabbi David which is...
I prepared, I wouldn't have known it otherwise, so sorry for jumping
it on you. It's the ראב״ד. Ra'avad. The ראב״ד. Ra'avad. And the
interesting thing that I came across in preparing is that תוספות Tosafot
quotes the ראב״ד Ra'avad only three times in the whole ש״ס. Shas.
You can go look for it in your free time. Here, I
wrote it down, יומא ותענית. Yoma veta'anit. Okay.
When was the ראב״ד? Ra'avad? Where else it says...?
Ah, I have all this.
1110 to 1180 in Spain, Cordoba. תוספות Tosafot is also around the
same like crusaders right, 1000 something like that and a collection. But
the ראב״ד, Ra'avad, okay. דודאי שלקות אסרו חכמים כשהעובד כוכבים מבשלם בביתו.
Devadai shlakot asru chachamim keshe'oved kochavim mevashelam beveito.
This is now the ראב״ד's Ra'avad opinion. Of course the שלקות shlakot
which is— the soup, right, this mixture of water and vegetable, is
forbidden, or the חכמים Chachamim forbade it when the עובד כוכבים oved
kochavim is cooking them in his, in the עובד כוכבים's oved kochavim
home. The pronouns here are problematic, who's his. So in the עובד
כוכבים. oved kochavim. אבל כשהוא מבשל בביתו של ישראל אין
לחוש, לא לחתנות ולא לשם יאכילנו דברים טמאים.
Aval kshe-hu mevashel beveito shel Yisrael ein lachosh, lo l'chatnut
velo l'shem yachilenu devarim tme'im. This is the הראב"ד Ravad's opinion which
will be rejected. Sadly or not sadly, right. So the הראב"ד Ravad
said if the non-Jew cooks at his, at the Jew's home.
To me that makes sense.
What, what are we worried about? There's no חתנות, chatnut, there's no
whatever, cooking together we're going to immediately get married. And we know
what the, what the non-Jew is putting in the food cause he's
cooking in my, he she's cooking in my kitchen. ולא הודה לו
רבנו תם. Velo hoda lo Rabbeinu Tam. רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam and
like the, the decisive voice in the תוספות Tosafot didn't accept this
הראב"ד Ravad's opinion, but I think it's important, it's important to know
that it's there. And תוספות Tosafot continue: דודאי כמשעובד כוכבים מבשל לא
חלקו כלל חכמים בין רשות הישראל לרשות העובד כוכבים.
Devadai kemshe'oved kochavim
mevashel lo chalku klal chachamim bein reshut haYisrael l'reshut ha'oved kochavim. We
didn't distinguish between whether he's cooking at his own home or at
the Jew's home. כי לעולם יש לחוש שמא לא יזהר גם בביתו
של ישראל כמו בביתו של עובד כוכבים. Ki le'olam yesh lachosh shema
lo yizaher gam beveito shel Yisrael kmo beveito shel oved kochavim. It's
possible that he won't be careful, maybe he's going to the market
and bringing ingredients to cook at the non-Jew's home.
That's not an issue of חתנות chatnut though, right? That's not...
It's not an issue of חתנות, chatnut, it's an issue of ingredients.
Look, חתנות chatnut is very complicated. I can give examples which I'm
not sure we want to go into where okay, let's say I'll
be the non-Jew who is working at the, Gloria's home, right? Okay,
and Gloria has a son, and I bring my daughter to cook
with me. Like, whatever, cooking can be a very intimate thing. If
you think about verbs connected with food, they're often connected with sexuality.
There is something about those two things that we can have a
whole long שיעור shiur about, which we're not,
but that they have, that there's some connection between them. So, I
get it. Intermarriage? Intermarriage.
חתונה. Chatuna. Oh, okay. חתנא. Chatna.
I understand,
I think it's important to note that the הראב"ד Ravad is here.
There is probably a reality to this in our own time too,
both in Israel and here where people, older people, whatever people that
need help, have somebody non-Jewish cooking at their home. So do you
always have to be there, right, to light, to watch, to intervene
in the cooking? Or is there an opinion that says the non-Jew
cooking in your house is okay? So I think it was nice
to know that it's here.
Moving right along at the top of ל"ח עמוד א. Lamed Chet
amud aleph.
The same question also comes out specifically in restaurants, right? You have
less of a problem of חתנות, chatnut, but you have more of
a problem of דבר טמא.
davar tamei. Yes, I mean we have a whole thing we're dealing
with now in Brooklyn, vegan restaurant, totally vegan, all ingredients okay.
What do we do with it? Okay.
You have Buddhist, you know, in Chinatown, kosher restaurant, you know what
I mean?
They don't have anything, any meat at all. What was the question?
What is the question? But then there are issues with leaves and
do they check the leaves, you know, like blah blah blah. So
it's not only meat or oils. Okay.
No I mean it has a, it has a השגחה.
hashgacha. השגחה. Hashgacha. I'm talking about a situation where in Brooklyn we
have a vegan restaurant with a השגחה hashgacha we're trying to check
if
it's real. No, no, I don't want to use the word real,
but just if we can use it for our specific community, yes.
So all these issues come into play. Who's cooking,
which, what do we go... Okay. Moving right along. אמר רב שמואל
בר יצחק אמר רב: כל הנאכל כמות שהוא חי אין
בו משום בישולי כוכבים.
Amar Rav Shmuel bar Yitzchak amar Rav: kol hane'echal kemot shehu chai
ein bo
mishum bishulei kochavim.
We can read it again. כל הנאכל כמות שהוא חי אין בו
משום בישולי עובדי כוכבים. Kol hane'echal kemot shehu chai ein bo mishum
bishulei ovdei kochavim. So something that is unchanged, that's back to the...
If it could be eaten... רגע. רגע. rega rega, כמות שהוא חי.
Kemot shehu chai.
We'll see, we'll see how it's worked with. בסורא מתנו הכי, בפומבדיתא
מתנו הכי. Besura matnu hachi, bePumbedita matnu hachi. So Sura, this is
how they taught. In Pumbedita, here is what they say about this.
אמר רב שמואל בר יצחק אמר רב: כל שאינו נאכל על שולחן
מלכים ללפת בו את הפת אין בו משום בישולי עובדי כוכבים.
Amar Rav Shmuel bar Yitzchak
amar Rav: kol she'eino ne'echal al shulchan melachim lelapet bo et hapat
ein bo mishum bishulei ovdei kochavim. So in Pumbedita something else was
added to this eating something חי chai is something that can be
eaten with the bread, ללפת בו את הפת. lelapet bo et hapat.
If you go to Israel you might have your falafel or shawarma
with a לאפה, laffa, right, ללפת lelapet to... to like wrap around
with bread.
Something that is eaten like by kings, huh?
That was the original כורך! korech!
That was the original thing. Right, right, see. And
מאי בינייהו, mai beineihiu, okay, what's the difference, what's between those two
opinions?
One is it's not eaten חי, chai, but it also does not
is not fit for kings.
And what are some of the things that are you know in
this
distinction
part? דגים קטנים dagim ktanim וארדי v'ardi ודיסא. v'daisa. דגים קטנים dagim
ktanim small fish, ארדי ardi
mushrooms, and דיסא daisa still to this very day,
porridge, not so much cereal grains but oatmeal or cream of wheat
and still to this day mothers will say "תירצה דיסא?" tirtze daisa?
huh?
דגים קטנים dagim ktanim are
not cooked, mushrooms also, דיסא daisa whatever, it's a something in between.
Okay. אמר רב אסי אמר רב דגים קטנים
מלוחים
אין בהם משום בישולי עובדי כוכבים.
Amar Rav Assi amar Rav dagim ktanim
mluchim
ein bahem mishum bishulei Ovedei Kochavim. So now there is a question
of the salting what does that do
to the small fish? Ceviche?
Yeah, I guess. And potentially, yeah. And
some of it we're doing בישול bishul in שבת Shabbos for somebody
that is not a big cook, this is all challenging. But things
that cook very quickly right, or cook by another process other than
really like boiling or baking for a long time, like the קלי
הבישול kalei habishul and here the מלוחים. meluchim. Okay.
אמר רב יוסף אם צלאן עובד כוכבים סומך ישראל עליהם משום עירובי
תבשילין ואי עבדינהו עובד כוכבים כסדא דהרסנא אסור.
Amar Rav Yosef im tzl'an Oved Kochavim somech Yisrael aleihem mishum
eiruvei tavshilin v'i avdinahu Oved Kochavim k'sada d'harsana assur. Okay,
if he fried them, that's Rav Yosef's opinion, if
he fries or roasts fish then that's that's okay, סומך ישראל עליהם
משום עירובי תבשילין, somech Yisrael aleihem mishum eiruvei tavshilin, we think that
they're part of other cooking,
ואי עבדינהו עובד כוכבים, v'i avdinahu Oved Kochavim, and if the non-Jew
made them into this dish that's called a כסדא דהרסנא ksada d'harsana
that's like a muryis, it's a fish with fish oil and it's
made with flour and oil and cooked, then that is forbidden. There
is something about this muryis that is made with vinegar and vinegar
we're suspicious that it's made from wine, right? That and wine is
יין נסך, yayin nesech, therefore mixed dancing is forbidden. Okay. פשיטא. Pshita.
Huh?
You're waiting for this? You got it. It's the biggest problem ever.
רגע
פשיטא מהו דתימא הרסנא עיקר קמ"ל קמחא עיקר.
Rega pshita mahu
d'teima harsana ikar kamashma lan kimcha ikar. Okay. So in this dish
of fish in the sauce of flour and oil or and this
vinegar thing, what is the עיקר? ikar? What is the main piece
about it? Might it be the kosher fish or might it be
the קמחא? kimcha? If it's the קמחא, kimcha, the קמחא kimcha is
not changed, right? It's just grounded and it's
and it's eaten as it is. But it can be,
if the קמחא kimcha is the עיקר ikar and it's not eaten
live because now it's mixed in this cooked thing, then it will
have an aspect of בישולי עכו"ם bishulei akum and it's
and it's not not allowed.
איכא בינייהו? Ika beineihiu? Yes, I have it marked. You want to
read? It's okay.
Because the תוספות Tosafot is asking about דבש וגבינה שעולים על שולחן
מלכים ונאכלים חיים, dvash u'gvina she'olim al shulchan melachim v'ne'echalim chaim, right?
We should have talked about things that are raw and are eaten
right? Because before we said in פומבדיתא Pumbedita לא עלו על שולחן
מלכים. lo alu al shulchan melachim. So what do we do with
things that are raw and are part of like, you know, festive
שולחן מלכים, shulchan melachim, I don't know if it's actual king or
like festive opportunities.
And then it say, he says שנעשה בהם לשון אחרון מוסף על
הראשון ולהקל עליו. shena'asa bahem lashon acharon musaf al harishon u'lehakel alav.
Okay. All right. moving on just for the sake of time.
Yeah, but look at the next one too, הרי שבישלן עובד כוכבים
אחר שמרחן ישראל. harei shebishlan Oved Kochavim achar shemerchan Yisrael. So who's
doing the salting? According to תוספות Tosafot you have to first have
it Jew salt it.
You have to have a Jew salt it. That's תוספות? Tosafot? Wait,
there's still more discussion about
all
this. Okay. Hold
no הלכה halakha yet, just situations and yes.
Okay. אמר רב ברונא אמר רב עובד כוכבים שהצית את האור באגם
כל החגבים שבאגם אסורים. Amar Rav Beruna Amar Rav oved kochavim she'itzit
et ha'ur be'agam kol hachagavim she'ba'agam asurin. Situation.
Situation, no objection yet. Just trying to understand the situation and an
idolater, עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim, that burned a meadow, אגם, agam, in
modern Hebrew like a lake, but more like a marsh maybe. Yes,
a marsh that has plants in it and I want to clear
that area so I can use it for planting.
Might be more of a בבל Bavel situation where the rivers flood
and so on, but like you know before the pioneers, right, we
saw it in the חולה. Hula.
You clear trees to,
you know, whatever underbrush to... Yeah, but אגם agam more marsh than
like big trees.
So more you want to drain the swamp or something. Yes, for
mosquitoes and...
Yeah. So you burn all this stuff so then stuff has not
to grow, okay. Not, doesn't have where to grow and you have
the dirt can be beneficial for agriculture.
Okay. So he lights the fire and now what is the rule
of the grasshoppers that if I walk in afterwards into this marsh
and there's dead grasshoppers that were likely roasted by this fire, can
I wrap them in my לאפה lafa and have them for dinner?
היכי דמי? heichi dami? Okay, so what, what exactly are we talking
about? Huh?
That's the biggest problem.
For some, I guess. So here what the situation, what, what we
want to לדקדק, ledakdek, what is, what is exactly that we're talking
about? The
person did, the non-Jew did not intend to cook, right? So is
intent part of our cooking? So
the
גמרא Gemara is trying to unpack it. Okay. אילימא דלא ידע היי
טהור והיי טמא מאי איריא עובד כוכבים אפילו ישראל נמי. ileima delo
yada hai tahor ve'hai tamei mai irya oved kochavim afilu Yisrael nami.
Like if the question is that we don't know which grasshopper is
טהור tahor and which is טמא, tamei, what does it matter who
light the, who lit the fire, right? We wouldn't have known if
it's ישראל נמי. Yisrael nami. אלא משום בישול עובדי כוכבים? ela mishum
bishul ovdei kochavim? Are we worried?
אלא ela that this case specifically had to do with,
let me see that I'm not mixing it up with... Yes, had
to do with... No, no, no. Yes, it's going to come back.
Sorry.
Had to do with,
we're examining whether it has to do with the עובדי כוכבים ovdei
kochavim because the טהור tahor and טמא tamei we excluded, right? It
can't be because of that because it wouldn't matter if it's a
Jew or not. Okay. כי האי גוונא מי אסיר? ki hai gavna
mi asir?
Who would forbid a case like this? We're bringing another case in
order to deal with the previous case. והא אמר רב חנן בר
אמי אמר רב אדא אמר רבי יוחנן האי עובד כוכבים דחריך רישא
שרי למיכל מיניה אפילו מריש אוזניה. ve'ha amar Rav Chanan bar Ami
amar Rav Adda amar Rabbi Yochanan hai oved kochavim decharich reisha shari
le'meichal minei afilu meresh ozneih. Okay, if we have, this is, this
is a teaching by רב חנן בר אמי אמר רב אדא אמר
רבי יוחנן Rav Chanan bar Ami amar Rav Adda amar Rabbi Yochanan
about a עובד כוכבים oved kochavim who singes the head of an
animal, and it is permitted to eat part of it, like he
singes the hair.
חרך charach in Arabic is to burn.
Yeah, and in modern Hebrew it's to singe.
No, but so maybe...
Oh, you think that it's to burn completely? How can you eat
it?
But they normally translate singe.
Yeah, you can eat, it's permitted to eat a part of it,
even the tip of the ear, which supposedly is a very soft
part, okay, so it would be fully cooked with the singeing. And
so what about that case? אלמא לאבורי שיער קמיכוין. alma le'avorei se'ar
kamichaven.
So here is a situation where the אקום, akum, the עובד כוכבים
oved kochavim intended to remove the hair. The intention was not to
cook, it was to remove the hair. In the process of this
intention, the ear got cooked. So here also we look at the
intent. He intended to clear the meadow, not to prepare a meal
of grasshoppers. Okay.
So yes, all that is true. Intent matters. לעולם דלא ידע היי
טהור והיי טמא. le'olam delo yada hai tahor ve'hai tamei. And
so now we say,
this
is a case where there's a mixture of grasshopper, locusts maybe better.
And they're forbidden when they're mixed together because we don't know which
one is טהור tahor and which one is טמא. tamei. ומעשה שהיה
בעובד כוכבים היה. U'ma'aseh shehayah b'oved kochavim hayah. It simply this specific
situation of somebody burning the meadow with the grasshoppers in it was
somebody who was an עובד כוכבים oved kochavim but could have been
a ישראל. Yisrael. At the moment there's no problem if we had
known which one is טהור tahor and which one is טמא. tamei.
So the cooking itself is not a problem because a grasshopper is
not what's called טעון שחיטה. ta'un shechitah. There's no שחיטה shechitah for
a grasshopper. So right now there's no problem. Okay.
Okay, so now let's look at more aspects of the cooking. גופא.
Gufah. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbah bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan.
These two are going to, we're going to have them for a
few, a little bit of the discussion so the relationship between them
is important. רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana is a
student of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, so maybe we'll see it in
a minute, twenty years after him. היי עובד כוכבים דחריך רישא שרי.
Hai oved kochavim decharich reisha sharei. So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says what we just mentioned, if the עובד
כוכבים oved kochavim singes the head in order to singe the hair,
then it's שרי למיכל מיניה אפילו מריש אוניא. sharei l'meichal minei afilu
mereish onya.
It's permitted to eat even from that soft ear, the tip of
the ear, which is completely cooked.
Wait, can I ask a question? When the idolater singes the hair,
is he doing it as an idolatrous act?
Presumably not, because otherwise we would not be able to eat it.
Right.
Let's assume he wants to get the hair off to use the
skin or something?
No, we're now in a head of an animal. I'm assuming grasshopper
we can't eat the ears. I don't know. Having not much experience
with either, I'm assuming ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
you want to put the head of your איל ayil on your
plate. Can you eat this ear?
I'm assuming that this is a situation where the עובד כוכבים oved
kochavim is cooking a kosher animal at the Jew's home. How,
where are we going with this, right? At what, what is the
threshold?
גמרא Gemara fifty shades of grey. Where in the grey are we
going to end up?
It's true. Where in the grey are we going to end up
that it's permitted or not? Okay. So what, what is the situation?
Because look, if it's for idolatrous practices, we can't eat it anyway.
If the non-Jew's cooking it at home and what, serving the Jew
an ear of an animal? Can't eat that. It has to be
a situation that it's even a question. It can only be a
question in the situation that we've discussed previously where the עובד כוכבים
oved kochavim might be cooking in the Jew's home. What does that
look like? And this is like whatever, we bring ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah as an example. Okay.
אמר רבינא: Amar Ravina: הלכך, Hilchach, this is how it goes. היי
עובד כוכבים דשדא סיכתא לאתונא וקבר בה ישראל קרא מעיקרא שפיר דמי.
Hai oved kochavim deshada sikta l'atuna v'kavar ba Yisrael
kra meikara shapir dami. Okay, so here is maybe a situation.
The Gentile is throwing a יתד, yated, peg,
okay, into the oven in order to, huh?
סיכתא, Sikta, modern Hebrew סיכה? sikah?
סיכה, Sikah, yeah, סיכה sikah modern Hebrew is usually metal. The understanding
is not like wood or something, maybe here is not wood either.
It's gotta be a material that he's trying to dry but not
burn. So again, the intent is not to cook in this fire
but to dry יתד yated in the תנור. tanur. Okay. וקבר בה
ישראל קרא. V'kavar ba Yisrael kra. The Jew put a דלעת, d'laat,
gourd, pumpkin, squash in it. מעיקרא שפיר דמי. Meikara shapir dami. פשיטא.
Pshita. Okay, so again, just hold the thought, we're going to unpack
which comes first, the chicken, the egg, the fire, the gourd. Okay.
מהו דתימא לבישולי מנא קא מיכוין. Mahu d'teima l'bishulei m'na ka michavein.
What is the intent here? His intent was to burn this peg,
right? The
עובד כוכבים oved kochavim
intended to just burn this יתד, yated, the peg, to soften
it or harden it, right? And so that was not the intention.
Now the question is where is this דלעת, d'laat, where is this
דלעת d'laat showed up? Did the דלעת? d'laat?
It says מעיקרא, meikara, which means he put it there first.
Right, so the דלעת d'laat is there and then the non-Jew comes
and lights the fire, but we're going to see that איפכא, ipcha,
there's also going to be situations
איפכא. ipcha.
Because there is an עניין inyan of whether it's חשיבות, hashivut, whether
it's like there is an intention or צריך tzarich like we talk
about מלאכת מחשבת, melechet machshevet, right, there has to be something that
was thoughtful in this. Let me see.
So the very last line of the תוספות Tosfot on this ל"ח
עמוד א' lamed chet amud aleph says אבל לעניין בשולי כוכבים לא
חשיב ואינו חייב עד שיתכוון לבישול גמור. aval le'inyan bishulei kochavim lo
chashiv ve'eino chayav ad she'itkaven lebishul gamur. There has to be an
intent of cooking, not just of the pig. This is my understanding.
Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הניח ישראל בשר על גחלים ובא
עובד כוכבים והפך בו מותר.
amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel heni'ach Yisrael basar al gechalim uva oved
kochavim
vehafach bo mutar. So if the Jew put the meat on the
coals and then the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim turned the coals, it's
okay. היכי דמי. heichi dami. אילימא דאי לא הפך בו הוה בשיל.
ilima de'i lo hafach bo hava bashil. So פשיטא. pishita. Like if
the non-Jew didn't play with the fire, the thing would have cooked
anyway. So that's not not an issue. אלא. ela.
Do you know in תוספות Tosfot where it says כמאן דאיתא כאן
וכאן יהא רבנו תם מתיר keman de'ita kan vechan yehe Rabbeinu Tam
matir something and something, you know those תוספות? Tosfot? Something with something,
I don't know what those are.
Which one are you?
The white lines, the first תוספות.
Tosfot. Oh,
what's this כתיש
ואובליא ktish ve'uvliya or something like this? So what dishes are those?
Yeah, I don't know, I don't
even know what that
is. Yeah, okay.
So
you know when I prepare, when I listen, there's a lot of
things that from this transfer to שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, what are
our practices today? And to רמב"ם, Rambam, not all in agreement with
each other of how we deal with this non-Jew's cooking in our
homes, which is super interesting. This was an issue for 2,000 years.
It means that we lived, yes, of course it's an issue now,
right, but it means that we lived in such close proximity with
the non-Jews for this to be for this to be a problem.
Okay. Okay.
היכי דמי. heichi dami. So what is our situation now with the
meat on the coals? אילימא דאי לא הפך בו הוה בשיל. ilima
de'i lo hafach bo hava bashil. So פשיטא, pishita, if we didn't
turn it, still would have cooked. אלא לאו דאי לא הפך לא
הוה בשיל אמאי מותר בישולי של עובדי כוכבים נינהו?
ela lav de'i lo hafach lo hava
bashil amai mutar bishulei shel ovdei kochavim ninhu? So
we're asking a question. Like if he's what if if
the
meat is on the coals and it would have cooked anyway and
the non-Jew plays with the fire, then it doesn't matter, would have
cooked anyway. But what if what if not? Why is it permitted?
Then it will be considered בישול עכו"ם. bishul akum. So, לא צריכא
דאי לא הפך הוה בשיל בתרתי שעי והשתא קבשל בחד שעה. lo
tzricha de'i lo hafach hava bashil betartei sha'ei vehashta kavashel bechad sha'ah.
So
if he didn't, we still need to say it because it still
would have cooked but much slower. If it wasn't turned it would
have cooked in two hours and like this it cooked in one
hour.
So in the matter of גזירה ובשולי עכו"ם, gzira u'vishulei akum, it's
not considered בישול. bishul. It would be okay. מהו דתימא קרובי בישולא
מילתא היא קמשמע לן. mahu deteima kruvei bishula milta hi kamashma lan.
So because it's so
if we say that hastening the cooking process is significant, therefore we
have to be taught otherwise, that that is not yet a problem.
Luckily for all of us, this discussion is definitely not over in
this דף daf and it's still going to continue in other places
in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and in other places in general. So
anything that's not answered, we're going to
visit
it again.
It shows that the Jewish-gentile relations were having a moment, definitely.
Yes,
it shows a lot of things. It's really interesting to study it
anthropologically, right? How did it work? But for the sake of time
and us only being at the bottom of ל"ח עמוד א', lamed
chet amud aleph, we're going to move a little bit. Next one
is for Gloria. והא אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן כל שהוא
כמאכל בן דרוסאי אין בו משום בשולי עובדי כוכבים הא אינו כמאכל
בן דרוסאי יש בו משום בשולי עובדי כוכבים.
veha amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan kol shehu kemachal ben drosai
ein bo mishum bishulei ovdei
kochavim ha eino kemachal ben drosai yesh bo mishum bishulei ovdei kochavim.
So since we're doing שבת, Shabbat, we're dealing with the מאכל בן
דרוסאי machal ben drosai extensively.
בן דרוסאי Ben Drosai is referenced to a... robber,
bandit, so he doesn't have a lot of time to spend with
the cooking and he eats things that are not fully cooked. So
how much not fully cooked can the not fully cooked be? Is
half enough? Like what if he cooked only 50%? That's good enough?
Huh?
Medium rare.
Medium, I don't know. Okay, see, I'm telling you, I don't know
the medium rare and all that. But this is a third cooked.
Okay? So if it's something that's a third cooked, אין בו משום
בישולי עובדי כוכבים ein bo mishum bishulei ovdei kochavim because and if
it's not a מאכל בן דרוסאי, ma'achal Ben Drusai, i.e., it's cooked
further, then יש בו משום בישולי עובדי כוכבים. yesh bo mishum bishulei
ovdei kochavim. By the
non-Jew. Yeah. Yeah, because
if it's more
than
a third by the non-Jew, it's a problem.
I'm semi-joking but I'm serious, like where are the lines inside the
gray? Yes, so if it's up to the מאכל בן דרוסאי? ma'achal
Ben Drusai?
Yeah, I see there's a...
it's a מחלוקת machloket if it's a half or a third. How
much not cooked can the not cooked thing be? Can the... no,
it's true.
By the non-Jew.
Like שקשוקה. shakshuka. It's exactly like that.
So it could be that the non-Jew could start it, cook it
a little bit, turn it...
I have to cook for Coop, okay? And I'm not cooking meat,
but let's say vegetables. Okay. So I don't want to mush them
completely because by the time I warm them up for lunch, they'll
be blah. So I'm going to half cook. Where is my half?
Is it like closer to the raw half or is it closer
to the mush half? Okay, so they want it to be in
the... there's a discussion whether half is in the third not cooked
or half might be later on. Okay. התם כגון אותיבי בסילתא ושקליה
עובד כוכבים ואותיבי בתנורא. Hatam kegon otivei
besilta vishaklei
oved kochavim veotivei
betanura.
So
the situation that רב אסי Rav Assi is referring to, a case
where the Jew placed the meat that was not yet fully cooked
like the בן דרוסאי Ben Drusai in a סילתא, silta, in a
basket where it would not have cooked at all and then the
non-Jew took it, the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim took it and placed
it in the oven. Again, trying to understand the mechanics of cooking,
where is the half cooked, right?
So this is who did it first?
Well, okay, so like let's say the meat is in the, whatever,
a basket. I don't know what it is doing there. It's thawing,
it's slow cooking, right? And now the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim comes
and puts it in the oven.
So where, how do we measure a third cooked? Is it the
third softness? Is it how much it went through? Is it how
much time? Well,
we
have that issue on בישול bishul for שבת Shabbos too.
Yes, exactly, exactly.
It's also about how hot
it is too, how fast it's cooking. That's the whole, that's the
whole thing. And this is why, so here we have some sort
of a cooking, right? Where the Jew placed the meat
that is not yet cooked, right, like the מאכל בן דרוסאי ma'achal
Ben Drusai inside some basket. I don't know where that basket is,
right?
But like where, that's what you're describing for Coop. You cooked it
partway, you put it in a basket to transport it,
and now it's going to be put in the oven by the,
whatever, somebody that works in the building comes and puts it in
the oven, right? How much could it have been cooked? Okay.
Moving
on. תניא נמי הכי מניח ישראל בשר על גחלים ובא עובד כוכבים
ומהפך בו עד שיבא ישראל מבית הכנסת או מבית המדרש ואינו חושש.
Tanya nami hachi maniach Yisrael basar al gechalim uva oved kochavim umehafech
bo ad sheyavo Yisrael mibeit haknesset o mibeit hamidrash ve'eino choshesh. So
the Jew puts a piece of meat on the coals and the
עובד כוכבים oved kochavim comes and turns it over, right, as necessary,
assuming,
until the Jew comes back from בית הכנסת beit haknesset or בית
המדרש. beit hamidrash. אין חדש תחת השמש. Ein chadash tachat hashemesh. Where
else could he be? Could he possibly have gone to work? No.
Let's assume שבת Shabbos situations or other situations, but very interesting. What
was your question?
So this is on שבת? Shabbos?
Not obvious.
Okay. ואינו חושש. Ve'eino choshesh. And again,
there's going to be a discussion whether this non-Jew that's dealing with
the food needs to have a שומר shomer because while let's say
we're having צולנט, cholent, right? Somebody can put something in it while
I'm not at home, right? So somebody can add something to the
cooking, anything from poison to something לא כשר, lo kasher, right, that
will enhance the flavor. So there's a question, which I'm not getting
into, I'm just parking, whether there is an assumption or a need
for a שומר. shomer.
Likewise, similar example.
שופטת אישה קדרה על גבי כירה ובאת עובדת כוכבים ומגיסה, shofetet ishah
kedeira al gabei keirah uvaat ovedet kochavim umegisah,
if the woman leaves a pot, just a second, on the כירה
keirah and the idolator comes and like stirs it, turns it with
a spoon, עד שתבוא מבית המרחץ או מבית הכנסת ואינה חוששת, ad
shetavo mibeit hamerchatz o mibeit haknesset veina chosheshet, likewise not worried. Okay,
yes.
Yes, I was just explaining in the case with the basket that
it was considered as if the Jew had completed his cooking and
then the non-Jew was beginning cooking again,
a new act of cooking, which was why it became prohibited,
unless it was cooked to the degree of בן דרוסאי Ben Drusai
or past it.
Past it. Okay. I have a lot of notes that I'm not
sure if you want to go into, but just FYI about this
like throwing a peg into the fire, what does that do to
the עובדי כוכבים? ovdei kochavim? The ראש Rosh says that this is
what they did in בבל. Bavel. Again, super interesting that they were
lenient about this, so if the non-Jew just threw something into the
fire, it was
what did it do? The בני מערב, Bnei Ma'arav, people of Israel,
said קיסם זה מה מעלה ומה מוריד, keisam zeh mah maaleh umah
morid, the קיסם, keisam, like what does it matter if you throw
a peg into the fire, like it doesn't change anything about the
cooking. And the ראש Rosh said it's forbidden to use this practice,
but he also said והנח לישראל שיהיו שוגגים, vehanach l'Yisrael sheyiyu shogegim,
which is interesting. Let them make mistakes, this is not the worst
of all. רמב"ם Rambam said it's permitted
and if a Jew, sorry, if the Jew threw even just a
peg into the fire while the non-Jew is cooking, it will make
it בישול ישראל bishul Yisrael and therefore will be permitted. The ראש
Rosh says no, it's not allowed because it's not enough intervention in
the cooking. If I walk by and I just throw something into
the fire, it's not enough intervention in the cooking. רמב"ם Rambam said
it's fine. שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch has a discussion about it and
to this day it's a מחלוקת machloket ספרדים Sefardim and אשכנזים, Ashkenazim,
where the אשכנזים Ashkenazim are מקילים mekilim and the ספרדים Sefardim say
you need to be more involved in the cooking. Yes, that you
know what's going on.
In a place where there's a tower where everybody uses the one
oven, you've got to be מקיל mekil or else you're going to
basically say fight with your non-Jew neighbors or you can't ever cook
things.
But
okay, well, I'm parking, I'm parking it. The to this day,
the אשכנזים Ashkenazim are the מקילים mekilim on this and the ספרדים
Sefardim will say no, you actually need to put things in the
oven and take them out. You need to be active participant in
the cooking and not just enough to throw something into the fire
and say you were there.
Does this relate to the idea that the Jew lights the fire
and then everything after that is permissible?
Yeah, that's the, that's the question here.
What's the answer? I'm asking for today.
אשכנזים Ashkenazim do this?
Yes. Oh, this is, this is,
the אשכנזים Ashkenazim are מקילים mekilim and the ספרדים Sefardim say just
that
question of who lights the fire.
And as אשכנזים Ashkenazim or
ספרדים, Sefardim, depending on the bit, they could say that could be
enough,
throwing the peg in the fire. And the talk I heard in
preparation, so everybody says oh, one situation where we should be אשכנזי,
Ashkenazi, right? And the rabbi says, rabbi says what about good food
on פסח? Pesach? אברם Avram set
sorry, we lost yet again. All right. Moving on. We're at the
top of ל"ח עמוד
ב', lamed chet amud bet, second, second line. איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu,
איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, הניח עובד כוכבים ואפך ישראל מהו? hiniach oved
kochavim vehafach Yisrael mahu? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק קל וחומר, amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak kal vachomer, וגמרו ביד עובד כוכבים מותר, ugemaro
beyad oved kochavim mutar,
גמרו ביד ישראל לא כל שכן? gemaro beyad Yisrael lo kol sheken?
Like okay, if the, so we had a situation that the Jew
came and then the עכו"ם akum turned it, and it was fine,
right? So now we have the opposite. The non-Jew put it and
the put the meat and the Jew turned it, then should be
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, no? Because when the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim
finished the cooking was okay, now when it's a Jew, should be
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. איתמר. itmar.
Okay.
Wait, doesn't that contradict the thing about only throwing?
רגע רגע, rega rega, we're like still in the discussion. We're not,
we don't have any הלכות ממש ממש הלכות. halachot mamash mamash halachot.
We are all, all in the discussion. It's more about the דין
קיסם. din keisam. Okay. איתמר נמי, itmar nami, אמר רבה בר בר
חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbah bar bar Chanah amar Rabbi Yochanan,
ואמרי לה אמר רב אחא בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, veamrei
lah amar Rav Acha bar bar Chanah amar Rabbi Yochanan, so somebody
from רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan students is teaching. בין שהניח עובד כוכבים
והפך ישראל Bein shehenich oved kochavim vehafach Yisrael בין שהניח ישראל ועבד
עובד כוכבים bein shehenich Yisrael ve'avad oved kochavim מותר mutar ואינו אסור
עד שתהא תחילתו וגמרו ביד עובד כוכבים. ve'eino assur ad shetehe techilato
ugemaro beyad oved kochavim. So the teaching we understand from רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is it doesn't matter if the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim
placed the meat and the Jew turned it over, or the Jew
placed the meat and the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim turned it over,
either way it's permitted.
ואינו אסור ve'eino assur עד שתהא תחילתו וגמרו ביד עובד כוכבים. ad
shetehe techilato ugemaro beyad oved kochavim. It's only forbidden when both, like
the whole process from beginning to end, is by the hands of
the, of the עובד כוכבים. oved kochavim. אמר רבינא Amar Ravina הלכתא
hilchata אריפתא arifta דשגר עובד כוכבים ואפה ישראל deshagar oved kochavim ve'afa
Yisrael אי נמי ee nami
שגר ישראל ואפה עובד כוכבים shagar Yisrael ve'afa oved kochavim אי נמי
ee nami שגר עובד כוכבים ואפה עובד כוכבים shagar oved kochavim ve'afa
oved kochavim ואתא ישראל וחתא בה חיתוי ve'ata Yisrael vechata bah chituy
שפיר דמי. shafir dami.
All right. This is like a, like a song we can make
from it. So there's a bread, there's this bread baked in an
oven that was lit by an עובד כוכבים oved kochavim and the
Jew came and baked it. That's okay.
Or alternatively, שגר ישראל ואפה עובד כוכבים, shagar Yisrael ve'afa oved kochavim,
so the Jew lit the oven and the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim
baked. Or alternatively,
the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim lit the oven and the עובד כוכבים
oved kochavim baked and then the Jew came and did this חיתוי
chituy business that we're dealing with on שבת Shabbos all the time,
this like stoking of the fire.
שפיר דמי, shafir dami, that's even, that's מספיק maspik and this is
a whole discussion of just previously mentioned how involved do we need
to be in the cooking process in order for it to be
our cooking process.
Okay.
דג מליח. dag maliach. Now a דג, dag, a דג, dag, a
fish
that is salted by the עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim,
discussion about that. And a discussion about an egg. The, the egg
is interesting because you're cooking,
might you be cooking the egg in the shell? What is the
destiny of the egg?
All right. דג מליח חזקיה שרי ורבי יוחנן אסר. dag maliach Chizkiyah
shari veRabbi Yochanan assur. Who could imagine that there would be any
disagreement about these things? So there is. Okay. ביצת צלויה בר קפרא
שרי ורבי יוחנן אסר. beitzat tzluyah Bar Kappara shari veRabbi Yochanan assur.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan forbids the דג dag and the egg and,
and the others permit. כי אתא רב דימי אמר Ki ata Rav
Dimi amar אחד דג מליח ואחד ביצת צלויה חזקיה ובר קפרא שרו
ורבי יוחנן אסר. echad dag maliach ve'echad beitzat tzluyah Chizkiyah uVar Kappara
sharu veRabbi Yochanan assur. So רב דימי Rav Dimi summarizes it for
us and he says the salted fish and the egg,
they are,
he tells us that חזקיה Chizkiyah and בר קפרא Bar Kappara permitted
it and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan forbade. According to this, salting something
does not constitute cooking and therefore is permitted to be eaten.
What about curing?
What is the process?
I don't know, like corned beef.
Okay so, so this is beef already. This is in the realm
of kosher animals that need kosher treatment. This is all, this is
all like, right? I don't know enough about meat, but this is
not,
not just fish too, lox, sable.
Yeah, okay, but then that's what we're talking about. We're talking about
fish.
He's not just talking about salting, he's talking about what if it's
cured, if
it's smoked.
Let's see where we're going.
Where you going?
Let's see where we're going. Let's just walk the walk. We don't
know yet. All right.
Story, fun story. רבי חייא פרוא איקלע לבי ריש גלותא.
Rabbi Chiya Parva ikla
levei Reish Galuta. He chanced to the home or arrived at the
home of the ריש גלותא, Reish Galuta, of the head of the
גלות. Galus. They asked him, אמרו ליה ביצת צלויה מאי? amru leh
beitzat tzluyah mai? אמר להו חזקיה ובר קפרא שרו ורבי יוחנן אסר.
amar lehu Chizkiyah uVar Kappara sharu veRabbi Yochanan assur. So he said
this is the teaching I know, these two guys permitted, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan forbade, ואין דבריו של אחד במקום שנים. ve'ein devarav shel
echad bimkom shenayim. We cannot take one opinion to contradict two, which
is interesting. Sometimes we use democracy in the גמרא Gemara and sometimes
not at all, right?
אמר להו רב זביד לא תציתו ליה הכי אמר אביי הלכתא כוותיה
דרבי יוחנן.
Amar lehu Rav Zevid
lo ttzitu leh hachi amar Abaye hilchata kevataiah deRabbi Yochanan. רב זביד
Rav Zevid came and said don't listen to him because I heard
אביי Abaye say that הלכה halacha is as רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
which means it is. Forbidden? No.
Well now it's tied to the two though, right? I mean if
you're going to go by numbers.
No no no, רגע Rega. רגע, Rega. different. It's different to say
David and Gloria forbid, no, permit,
right?
Let's say Michael, and
Michael forbids, right? Then Hanan says, "I heard Michael say it's forbidden."
It's not your opinion. You're delivering somebody else's opinion and you say
Michael's more important than the two of them and therefore it's forbidden.
Guess what happened to him? He will not do this again. אשקיוה
נגוטא דחלא ונח נפשיה. Ashkyuha naguta de-chala ve-nach nafshei. So רב זביד
Rav Zvid who came and said, "Don't listen to these two מקילים,
mekilim, חס וחלילה chas ve-chalila you're going to eat the fish and
the egg. Go with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that forbid. I heard
that this is the right הלכה." halacha. They had him drink a
cup of this נגוטא, naguta, like spiced vinegar or some sort of
a drink, and he's resting ever since. נח נפשיה, nach nafshei, which
is the גמרא Gemara way of saying he died. I actually think
we should highlight this story. I actually think we should highlight this
story where the גמרא Gemara is saying, this is what I hear
the גמרא Gemara saying. You're welcome to hear other things completely, but
I hear the גמרא Gemara saying, "Enough חומרות, chumrot, עד כאן." ad
kan.
If you want to be מחמיר machmir on a thing we're already
חמור chamur with, this is like, this is not a בהמה, behema,
right? This is like, I mean, we're in the middle of the
gray. We're talking about the fish and the eggs, which should have
no problem. And you want to be חמור? chamur? No. Go away.
We don't want you.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Slightly moving on, yes, possibly. Let's make some,
get some ground. Okay. הקפריסין והקפלוטות והמטליא והחמין והקליות שלהן מותרין ביצה
צלויה אסורה שמן רבי יהודה הנשיא ובית דינו נמנו עליו והתירוהו.
Ha-kafrisin ve-ha-kaflotot ve-ha-matlya ve-ha-chamin ve-ha-kalyot she-lahen mutarin beitzah tzluyah asurah shemen Rabbi
Yehuda HaNasi ve-beit dino nimnu
alav ve-hitiruhu. Okay, we
still have a problem with the egg, no final, because now we
bring a תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, right, into
the discussion. And we have a few foods to pay attention to.
כפריסין, kafrisin, I have a picture on my phone I will show
you after the class. It's a plant that's in modern Hebrew is
called the צלף, tzelaf, it's capers. The capers that we use for
whatever,
right,
bagel and cream cheese and this and this and that. Okay, וקפלוטות
ve-kaflotot are leeks or onions, kind of plants. והמטליא, ve-ha-matlya, we'll have
a discussion. והחמין, ve-ha-chamin, hot water. והקליות, ve-ha-kalyot, roasted grains, that belong
to the non-Jews and were cooked by them are permitted. The egg
is forbidden according to this, and with oil, רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi
Yehuda HaNasi and his court are saying they checked it and they
said fine. תניא. Tanya. What is this מטליא matlya that we just
mentioned?
המטליא היא פשליא היא שיעתא. Ha-matlya hi pashlya hi shiata. So now
we just said the thing we don't know what it is is
something else we don't know what it is and it's also something
else we don't know what it is. מאי שיעתא? Mai shiata? What
is it that you're talking about? אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan. Remember that
team that repeats for us in this דף, daf, that רבה בר
בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana is a student of
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. הא ארבעין שנין דנפיק האי עובדא ממצרים. Ha
arbain shnin de-nafik hai uvda mi-Mitzrayim. ורבה בר בר חנה דידיה אמר
הא שיתין שנין דנפיק האי עובדא ממצרים. Ve-Rabba bar bar Chana deidei
amar ha shitin shnin de-nafik hai uvda mi-Mitzrayim. ולא פליגי מר בשניה
ומר בשניה. Velo pligi mar bishneia ve-mar bishneia. Because there's a difference
between them, right? They're not at the same time. רבה בר בר
חנה Rabba bar bar Chana is a student of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. There's twenty years between them. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it's
been forty years and, no,
yes, yes, yes, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan forty years and רבה בר
בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana says it's been sixty years since
this thing has come out, emerged from Egypt. It's a new discovery
that was made in, right, in America in חוץ לארץ. chutza la-aretz.
They don't disagree because each one of them has a different calculation
from their era. And what is it? Tell us, tell us, do
tell us. What is this שיעתא shiata thing?
מייתו ביזרא דכרפסא. Mayitu bizra de-charpasa. כרפס, karpas, right,
parsley or,
no, what's it called, celery kind of thing.
Cress, they say.
Okay, רגע, rega, there's a few ingredients in this thing. Okay. So
there's
ביזרא דכרפסא וביזרא דכיתנא וביזרא דשבליליתא. bizra de-charpasa u-bizra de-chitna u-bizra de-shavlilita.
So we take these seeds of parsley, flax, and fenugreek, this what
I have.
Sorry.
And soak them together וטרו להו בהדי הדדי v'taru lehu b'hadei hadei
בפשורי, b'pishurei, which soak them in lukewarm water, ושבקו להו עד דמקבלי,
v'shavku lehu ad d'mekablei, they, we let them soak until they sprout.
Okay.
ומייתי חצבי חדתא. u'maiti chatzavei chadata. So we put, we take I
have a pot like earthenware, red earthenware pot. מלו להו מיא, malu
lehu maya, we put water in
it, וטרו ביה גרגשתא. v'taru bei gargishta. So we put like some
form of red clay that we soak in it, ומדבקין ביה, u'medavkin
bei, we stick it, we stick it in this,
ואיילי לבי בני. v'ayli l'vei banei. They meanwhile go to the bathhouse.
Okay, so before going to the bathhouse we take these seeds and
we make this mixture and we put it like right, kids in
preschool put seeds on the cotton and all that. So we do
this whole thing in the pot.
אדנפקו מלבלבי. ad'nafku m'lavlavei. When we come out of the bathhouse these
things are already sprouting and they're blossoming ואכלי מיניהו, v'achli mineihu, and
they ate from it. This is this new Chia thing, right? Get
it on Amazon. וקיירי מבינתא דרשיהו עד טופרא דכרעיהו, v'kairi m'binta d'rasheihu
ad tufra d'charei'eihu, and it cools the body after the heat of
the bathhouse from the top of the hair, from the top of
the head until the טופרא, tufra, until the toenails of the feet.
איזה יופי. eize yofi. Okay, Rav Ashi says, Rabbi Chanina says, wait
a second, where is this? Yes.
אמר רב אשי אמר לי רבי חנינא מילין ואמרי לה במילין. amar
Rav Ashi amar li Rabbi Chanina milin v'amri lah b'milin. Okay, Rav
Ashi says that it's like, no, it's סתם stam stories.
I always like to find ways to explain the סתם stam stories
that they come up with. Okay, so maybe each one goes in
and picks something that grew a month earlier or whatever. What is,
what is this thing that is כזב? kazav? What is this thing
that's not true about it? Is it the process itself or is
it the fact that it blossomed, right, when you come out of
the bathhouse? Okay. ואמרי לה במילין. v'amri lah b'milin. So some say
that it's not that it's faulty, but that it was like magic
work and they would, they would
through magic words this would grow.
במילין, b'milin, yes. Some say מילין, milin, like מילין milin it was
just שטויות, shtuyot, and some say במילין b'milin that yes, through magic
they did it. All right, a little more if everybody's okay.
That's the whole difference between people who believe in the whole, you
know, you can take that in a very deep way. What? If
it to revelation? Somebody says it's just words and another person will
say but that is really the essence of, what,
what is the power
of, right, right, right. No, but by סתם stam words they mean,
no, it's like it never happened.
No, that's what I mean, believer and non-believer would say it's just,
right. I mean, I'm, I'm, I'm just saying you could.
Yeah, no, no, no, I always want to have a, not generous,
how do you call it, reading of the text, right.
I mean I'm not saying that they're saying that, I'm saying that
you
could also,
maybe generous, like you know trying to figure out how it could
have happened. But this is them themselves criticizing their own stories. Okay,
a little more. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. הכוספן של עובדי כוכבים שהוחמו
חמין ביורה גדולה אסור ביורה קטנה מותר. ha'kuspan shel ovdei kochavim she'huchmu
chamin b'yorah gedolah assur b'yorah ketanah mutar. What is a כוספן? kuspan?
Another great dish we should all try. This is alcoholic beverage made
from garbage of, made from dates or
from
yes, like from things that the dates were, were soaked in. Okay.
ביורה גדולה אסור ביורה קטנה מותר. b'yorah gedolah assur b'yorah ketanah mutar.
If it's a big pot it's forbidden, if it's a small pot
it's permitted. ואיזו היא יורה קטנה אמר רבי ינאי כל שאין ציפור
דרור יכול להיכנס בתוכה. v'eizo hi yorah ketanah amar Rabbi Yannai kol
she'ein tzipor dror yachol lehikanes b'tocha. What is the, what is the
definition of יורה קטנה? yorah ketanah? That a tiny sparrow bird can't
get into it. So really what they're talking about in a minute,
it's that the pot can be any size big you want, but
this opening has to be small that even a bird can't get
in. Why? We're worried about people putting things into it, right? We're
worried about something else swimming,
swimming in it. ודילמא אדמועי אדמעה ואילויי אילוייה, v'dilma admuei admueh v'iluyei
iluyeh, like, like okay, maybe they took the little tiny bird and
they cut it, chopped it into pieces and then they stuffed it
inside.
So no, be specific.
אלא כל שאין ראש ציפור דרור
יכול. ela kol she'ein rosh tzipor
dror yachol. Not the whole bird but just the head
can't get into it. Okay. So even a tiny piece cannot be
into it. והתניא, Vehatanya,
but isn't it taught in the ברייתא: Beraita: אחת יורה גדולה ואחת
יורה קטנה מותר. Achat yora gedola ve'achat yora ktana mutar. So we
have a conflicting source that says that it doesn't matter what the
size of the יורה yora is, it's permitted.
לא קשיא, La kashya,
no problem. הא כמאן דאמר נותן טעם לפגם אסור הא כמאן דאמר
נותן טעם לפגם מותר. Ha keman d'amar noten taam lifgam assur, ha
keman d'amar noten taam lifgam mutar. Okay, so now we have this
whole expression which maybe
as much time as we want to spend on it is what
is this טעם לפגם, taam lifgam, which is still an expression in
modern Hebrew where something happens and you say, yeah, it was fine
but there's טעם לפגם. taam lifgam. So there is flavoring in the
walls of this thing and what does the flavoring do? Is it
is it good or is it bad? Is it adding to us
or is it not adding? If it's bad, we will know that
there was some other flavoring in it. We'll be able to identify
it. If it's good, maybe maybe not. So there's a discussion and
that discussion, you'll be pleased to know, will continue on דף סז,
Daf Samech-Zayin, so we have not we're not ruling on anything.
It's super interesting.
I had the honor and the pleasure once to visit the Jack
Daniel's factory. Distillery, the
distillery. And they actually, like, these kind of things concern them, what
kind of barrels you put the whiskey in, because you can get
barrels that there was wine in and the the taste, the flavor
of the wine from the barrel will seep into the whiskey and
change, you know, the flavor of the whiskey and make it something
or another. Okay. Little more or how's our time? Kind of tight.
We
had
this נותן טעם לפגם noten taam lifgam a couple of pages ago.
Yes. And it's it'll continue. We're not we're not done. Continue.
Okay.
אמר רב ששת: Amar Rav Sheshet: האי משחא שלקא דארמאי אסור. Hai
mishcha shlaka d'Armai assur. Okay, this oil that was משחא, mishcha, nice.
משחא Mishcha still like an ointment, that was cooked by Aramean, by
an עובד כוכבים, Oved Kochavim, is forbidden. אמר רב ספרא: Amar Rav
Safra: למה ניחוש לה? L'mai nichosh leh? Like what what exactly what
should we be concerned about? אי משום ערובי מסרסרי. Ee mishum eruvi
masreseri. אי משום בישולי עובדי כוכבים נאכל כמו שהוא חי. Ee mishum
bishulei ovdei kochavim ne'echal kemo shehu chai. אי משום געולי עובדי כוכבים
נותן טעם לפגם הוא ומותר. Ee mishum ge'ulei ovdei kochavim noten taam
lifgam hu umutar. So what are the possibilities that this oil that
was cooked, right, by the עובד כוכבים oved kochavim is forbidden? Because
we said earlier that the oil, רבי יהודה נשיא, Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah,
נמנו על השמן nimnu al hashemen and they permitted. So what can
be this situation? If we're worried that vinegar, that something was ערוב,
eruv, something was mixed in it, if we're worried that it's vinegar,
which means wine which could mean idolatrous wine, that thing has a
smell, so we will recognize it right away, this like stench of
the חומץ, chometz, and we will know not to use, so it
doesn't doesn't have to tell us. אי משום בישולי עובדי כוכבים, Ee
mishum bishulei ovdei kochavim, it's חי, chai, so it's eaten raw, so
used raw, so doesn't matter.
And if it's משום געולי עובדי כוכבים, mishum ge'ulei ovdei kochavim, then
we have back to this issue of נותן טעם לפגם הוא. noten
taam lifgam hu. It imparts a flavor that can be like whatever,
not good for the mixture, and that's a continuous discussion, and in
this case, this is permitted. What's
געול? ge'ul?
געולי
עובדי כוכבים Ge'ulei ovdei kochavim is not cooking but like some residue,
right, or like something that's
cooked in a vessel of that has some
some leftover in it. Not leftover food, but like in the vessel
itself. Could
you
could you remind me of the context that we had discussed it
I guess yesterday of רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi had rescinded
the ban on idolatrous oil?
We had it just like a little while ago.
Yeah. So but why did he do that? In other words, was
there not a concern that it was used for idolatry?
I don't remember the reason but we just read it a few
lines
back which now I'm not going to find.
Here, just in the first line of the
wide. We can
see if there is a
further issue.
A few notes here on the side. I'm not... I don't have
the reason right now,
but maybe in my notes.
Yes, there is a תוספות Tosfot that's interesting.
One תוספות Tosfot on the top of ל״ח ב, Lamed Chet Bet,
if you're interested, this is about the pagan and the fire and
the בני בבל ותלמודם ובני מערבא Bnei Bavel v'Talmudam u'Vnei Maarava and
a discussion between Israel and בבל. Bavel. But at the bottom, two,
four, five, not sure if I can do this, והיינו טעמא לפי
שהוא ספק ספיקא. V'hainu taama lefi shehu sfek sfeka. So we have
two doubts on this extra flavor. ספק נשתמשו בו היום או אתמול
ואפילו נשתמשו בו היום שמא נשתמשו בו דבר שהוא פוגם Safek nishtamshu
bo hayom o etmol v'afilu nishtamshu bo hayom shema nishtamshu bo davar
shehu pogem from scribbles I can't see what I wrote
on it, או דבר שאין נותן טעם. o davar she'ein noten taam.
So one, we don't know when it was used and one we
don't know what was used in it. So there's two ספקות sfekot
and therefore מותר. mutar.
This was the כוספאן, Kusfan, that wine from dates that we're all
going to try, right? Okay.
Another dilemma raised. בעו מיני מרבי אסי הני אהיני שלקי דארמאי מהי?
Ba'u minei me'Rabbi Assi
hanei ahini shlakei d'Aramaye mahi?
So now we're asking a question with regards to these boiled dates,
the שלקי... shlakei... Okay, yes. אהיני
שלקי
דארמאי,
Ahini shlakei
d'Aramaye,
this Aramean boiled dates, what is the הלכה? halacha? We're asking before
רב אסי. Rav Assi. חולי לא תיבעי לך דודאי שרו. Cholei lo
tiba'i lach d'vadai sharu.
If these dates are sweet,
then obviously it's permitted because nothing was added to it. It's just
dates as is. We assume, era before white sugar and other additives,
right? מרירי לא תיבעי לך דודאי אסירי. Meriri lo tiba'i lach d'vadai
assiri. If it's bitter, then it was cooked, then it was cooked
with mixed dancing. Then it was cooked with vinegar, vinegar comes from
wine, wine possibly comes from idolatrous practices, therefore definitely forbidden. כי תיבעי
לך מציעא מאי? Ki tiba'i lach mtziya mai? So we are worried
in the middle again. Sweet we know is permitted,
bitter we know is אסור. assur. What about the middle? אמר להו
מאי תיבעי להו דרבי אסר ומנהו לוי. Amar lehu mai tiba'i lahu
d'Rabi assar u'manhu Levi. So he says what about this...
what about this middle?
We have an issue that it's חי, chai, right? It was not
cooked, we're just worried about the additives. The sweet doesn't have additives
because otherwise we would have felt it. The bitter might have additives,
therefore definitely forbidden. The middle, he says, my רבי Rebbe forbade. Who's
your רבי? Rebbe? לוי. Levi. Okay, then we will go with לוי.
Levi. We have another exciting dish, a שטיתא. shtita. שטיתא, shtita, רש״י
Rashi says, תבשיל העשוי מקמח של קליות שיבשן בתנור ויש עושים אותו
מקמח עדשים ולפי שהן מתוקים יותר מדי נותן שם חומץ. tavshil ha'asui
mi'kemach shel kliyot she'yibeshan ba'tanur v'yesh osim oto mi'kemach adashim v'lefi shehen
metukim yoter midai noten sham chometz. Okay,
so the שטיתא, shtita, I'm okay to stop if you guys need
to go, so we can be respectful of time. We'll just explain
the שטיתא shtita and then we'll bookmark it for tomorrow. The שטיתא
shtita is a grain and it can be made from two... it's
a dish that can be made from two different grains. It can
be lentils or it can be wheat. The lentils are sweet, therefore
because it's sweet we're going to... we might mix it up with
vinegar, which is made from wine, which could be from idolatrous practices.
And so now we're going to discuss how we're using this שטיתא
shtita and bring a story from King David as a proof and
have a great time. Thank you for being in גמרא Gemara cooking
this morning.
Have a fabulous
day, להתראות. l'hitraot. We could...
if you want to see the...
I'm sure there are people who try to like make these dishes
or something like that, like figure out, you know. Oh yes, there
must be people. There are always people who do.
Oh, that try to do גמרא Gemara cooking?
Yes, I'm sure there are people you know.
The plant that I wanted to show... The plant that I wanted
to show, here.
Now
you might know it, this is from ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It looks like
this, it grows, and it's called, it grows everywhere, and the seeds
of it are the capers. Oops,
sorry. These are
the, well, they're
the berries, they're called אביונות. evyonot. The caper plant is the צלף.
tzalaf. And the seeds are called אביונות. evyonot. And then there's the
caper itself, the flowers, the leaves, and they're called קפריסין. kafrisin. And
there are whole הלכות halachot about which one do you have to
say which ברכה beracha on, because they're essentially different parts of the
same plant. Wait, are they all on one plant? The caper, the
berry, and the leaf are all from the same plant. I'll look
that up. Yes, and they're all edible. Let me show you. They
have a very distinct, look at this. It's like a little, it's
a bud. Yes, exactly.